A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1904 June 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 5:4)
      Waited to thank him for letter, but it was saddening with its tale of overwork and overstrain because there have been elements of uncertainty and tension and confusion in his own situation. His feet now firm enough to ask if it's in his power to get to him for the winter. He would be delighted. James leaves for the United States the last week of August. Always full of tender and affectionate welcome in his own quiet way. Anderson's taking a long, costly journey sticks in his crop. He could cherish him for 3-4 weeks. The change would make for his comfort and well being. Thinks of him with anxiety and commiseration in the fiery furnace of Rome. #6251
    - Henry James to [Angelina] Milman, 1904 August 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Thanks for her word of sympathy and of warning. Her friend's slim volume came, but he cannot deal with it. Dreads the new book that is an appeal to and surrender of one's time from amateurish hands, and he is hardened to acknowledge many things by silence. Joy in swift slipping of time for his return to England, which one's advancing maturity makes generally more and more familiar. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1904 August 10, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 5:6)
      Talks about his charming touching letter. Every word as soothing as a caress. Money in his pocket if he knows Anderson is in a good high place at peace with his human companion, including brother Arthur. Groans over it being so long before he hears of his Italian summer. Will leave August 1 and not return until late spring. May his time be full without a blink of giddiness. Talks about photographs which terrify him with their evidence of madness. Talks at length about works shown in the photographs. Forgive him his wild and wandering talk. Pats him on his back tenderly. #6251
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1904 August 15, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. with envelope; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:7)
      Will have struck her that he was behaving with brutish want of grace. Can only throw it, with the dead weight of the rest of him, straight into scale, not of her justice, but of her mercy. Will go off to America in a few days. Unfinished work rode him like a nightmare. Book is done. Gives more excuses for not writing. Doubts if he shall hear from her again, but gives her his good wishes. Why doesn't she come to United States? She could have great success there, and enlarge her public and popularity. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1904 August 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:8)
      Only a word to announce the arrival of luminous pictures, which dazzle his eyes. Sails the 24th, but to the Reform Club, Pall Mall tomorrow. #6251-o
    - Brown, Shipley, & Co. to Henry James, 1904 August 20, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:9)
      They have received on his account from their Boston House, 33 pounds 15/7 shillings which they placed to his credit in their books. #6251-aq
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1904 August 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:10)
      Much touched by her generous letter letting him down so gently and humanely. Thanks for her handsome response to his imperfect plea. Talks of her sad situation at Alderburgh: tragic, insoluble, with her stricken mother, etc. These are terrible mortal hours, but sit tight and time will come when problems become shortened and softened. Sails for United States Wednesday, and they will foregather in the spring. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1904 September 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 5:11)
      What a generous, charming and interesting letter which came at the eleventh hour, which is infinitely treacherous. It is easy to neglect or forget the old world one has quitted, or forget it for a time, and only come back to it with such a rush. Has not made plans for the six to eight months that he had in mind. Has been there just a week in a vast yet exquisite Arcadia. The New England September is glorious and golden. Owes her recognition of her liberal response to his ineffectual expression re her brother. Asks her to feel him holding on to her tight with one hand, oh, so tight. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Miss Crawdace, 1904 September 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:12)
      Only in America a few days, and his daily postbag is appallingly heavy. Apology for thanking her in brief terms for her letter. James likes to know she is an intelligent and perceptive reader of his poor distillations. In the case of W.W.G. book from very bare commentary material made the thing a feat of ingenuity and almost literary heroism. There was little material on hand for a real record. Later in winter hopes for a pilgrimage to California, and shall perhaps have the pleasure of seeing her. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1904 December 9, ALS, 10 pp. on 5 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:13)
      Three days ago saw his sister in Boston. Thanks Anderson for the tender letter which he repeatedly re-read. Miserably mute because of all delays, shortcomings and embarrassments in America. Scapegoat of his conscience from day to day and hour to hour. Talks of Mrs. Andreas and her answers to questions about Anderson in Boston. What a shock to learn of Anderson's heart trouble and troubled pilgrimage to Turin specialist. Hopes Mrs. Andreas' report isn't too rose-coloured. Work gently and sanely. Put on brake and twiddle his thumbs. Wishes he could lay his hands, soothing, perhaps healing, on Anderson in the quality of their pressure. Mrs. Andreas showed him a photo album of Anderson's recent life and work. Pictures quickened his conception of his work's greatness and beauty. If he thought he was killing himself, James would come and smash a few dozen statues, smash them for brazen idols feeding on his flesh to clear the air. Photos bring tears to his eyes. Wanted to borrow the volume. Talks of the beauty of New England, and says he wants to see the rest of the country with some literary purpose until late in the spring, if he doesn't break down from weariness and nostalgia. New York affects him fearfully, and full of all sorts of homesickness, but interested, too; everyone is extraordinarily kind. Holds him in love. Keep up his heart and swing his hammer wide, and they will know good days together again. #6251
    - Henry James to "Dear Sirs" [Harper & Brothers], 1904 December 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:14)
      His brother, Professor James, indicated to him their inquiry as to his whereabouts. Doesn't wonder they are bewildered at his failure to stay in New York. Hopes to settle himself there by the first of the month. Delayed by having a dreadful condition in his hands which has lasted a month, blighted his days and nights and breaking into his work. Worst is over, and he is promised liberation and will go to 21 East 11th Street New York until February 10. #6251-a
    - Henry James to "Dear Madam," 1905 January 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:15)
      Her inquiry as to 2-3 of his letters among Miss Cobb's relics finds him spending a few months in America. She is welcome to print small documents in question if she thinks them worth it. Has no recollection of their contents or having written about Mrs. Kemble. Leaves matter to her discretion to use for her memorial or to recall a little of Mrs. [Frances Anne] Kemble's great presence. She has a free hand. #6251-y
    - Henry James to A[lvin] L[angdon] Coburn, 1905 January 27, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:16)
      In reply to his invitation to sit for photograph mentioned in letter to James from R. W. Gilder, he wishes to say he is far from New York and on his way south and to California, and shall not be in New York for weeks. Try him toward the end of April. #6251-g
    - H[enry] J[ames] to Mr. [Duneka], 1905 May 4, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 5:17)
      Obliged to his note confirming James's doing two New York papers for Harper's as soon as he can. Heine in London and Houghton will have projected a volume comprising a number of his early papers on English aspects and images, with illustrations by Joseph Pennell, a companion volume to James's Little Tour of France written 3-4 years ago and reissued. Duneka's firm controls situation of Essays, etc. there with Mr. McIlvaine. Houghton writing Duneka today. #6251-z
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1905 May 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:18)
      Sends a few words to bless him as he begins his course. Saw Alicia Anderson who showed him photos of his magnificent figure, which was a joy to behold. Proud of his genius. Hard to hear of his continued attacks of vertigo. Hard to think of his solitary voyage, being affected by the heart and that James might fail to see him. Sails for England July 4. Will be in Boston in late June. Told of his plans to sail from Genoa early in summer. Shall be back in Lamb House July 15. His monuments are over the head of all the "stupids" there, but there are individuals who are not impenetrable and hopes that for them he is bringing large pleasure. The man stretching his mighty arms is very great triumph, the finest thing he has done. #6251
    - Henry James to Louise [C. Walsh], 1905 May 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:19)
      Thanks for her note with sympathy for her bereavement. The 26th the more advisable day and will take the 4:09 from Grand Central. May she live gently in her altered state and life. #6251-al, #6251-bj
    - Henry James to [Frederick Allen King], 1905 July 2, TLS photocopy, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 5:20)
      Answering his questions on his preparation of bibliography of James's writings. He abhors bibliography, and his principle is to find it impossible to give them any furtherance. His unearthing early unsigned reviews in the Atlantic and North American Review only fills him with the bitterness of woe. Of article contributed to Balleon Post, Boston, 1871, he has no recollection. "Cousin et Cousine," 1876, must have been a translation of "Four Meetings," he is at sea about them. His good will almost brings to his eyes tears of remonstrance for misapplied effort. His asking where "Transatlantic Sketches" appeared makes him wonder why and how any such wretched little question can matter to anyone. Helps no intelligence to feed itself on such twaddle; millions of miles removed from any real critical play of mind. With note from Ned [Berkeley] to Waller [Barrett], n.d. #6251-aa
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1905 July 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:21)
      Sails tomorrow morning, and goes without seeing him. Will write if things are going well, and when he will return. Hopes he is feeling better. #6251
    - Henry James to Violet Hunt, 1905 July 18, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:22)
      May he come to tea on Tuesday the 28th? Shall be in town. Forgive frantic brevity. Returned from America Thursday. He is under mountain of arrears; squeaks from under it like a mouse. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], [1905] July 21, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:23)
      Since she gave the option, he can manage club lunch on the 25th. Doesn't know its name, but knows its door. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1905 August 6, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:24)
      His letter from Gibraltar is a sad enough story. Prepared for his visit in vain. Remembers their first hour together in Boston, etc. When shall they meet again? Grim years pass. His time in America was to his profit and gain. Non-communication difficult, as weighty things about his priority, work, plans, fountain must be discussed. Could have talked beautifully and intimately there [Rye] but they have to wait too long. Still wondering what American community is going to want to pay for thirty to forty stark naked men and women of whatever beauty, and lifted into raw light of a public place. Hideous he's not there and wants to be. Glad he is physically well and confident. #6251
    - Henry James to Walter B[erry] 1905 August 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. photocopy with typed transcript. (Box-folder 5:25)
      Hears nothing. What has become of him? Afraid he may have fled. Takes refuge that he may be free to come down to him for day or two. Write that he may look for a couple of nights of him. Original tipped into Letters of Henry James to Walter Berry, PS 2123.A53 B4 1928. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, 1905 August 8, ALS, 5 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 5:26)
      Feels deplorable not to have acknowledged The Marriage of William Ashe, which awaited him on his return from America three weeks ago. Returned amid much confusion and many complications, correspondence, etc. after nearly a year's absence. Hasn't yet been able to put himself into possession of William Ashe. Everyone in the United States was reading him, but will finally overtake it. Asks her to accept a copy of an American edition of The Golden Bowl. Appalled in returning to England, to see the awful shape Methuen had put it, in which no one has been able to read it. Heaven speed the day they may meet. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1905 August 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 5:27)
      Thanks him for the postcard. If Anderson could only do a pot boiler like that Atlas. Write him from Montefiascone to make up for James' lacking Anderson. Tell him of any good that came to him in the United States. If only Anderson could have been with him. #6251
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1905 November 5, ALS, 10 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 5:28)
      Horrible that James is so silent: their letters are grand little moments. Wanted to send Quarterly Review and his article. When he thinks of Anderson in Rome restored to his expensive family of naked sons and daughters of all sizes and ages, to say nothing of prancing animals, he knows not what to imagine. Applauds his courage and gallantry of his purpose, patience and concentration with all his heart, and prays powers may be given his aged eyes to see him successfully through again goes over their too few American hours and all they did. #6251
    - Henry James to [William] Morton [Fullerton?], 1905 December 17, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 5:29)
      Can't keep his hands off him. His sense of wonder in reading his little French volume so insists on overflowering. Finds him strangely interesting. Lost in admiration of his so cunning, so savante French form: it is performance of a brilliant and difficult feat, brought off so remarkably; as well as the way of so intimate a visitation of the marvelous old France of which it has been his own pathetic fate to see so little. Will dream to make up for that. Reading has always been experience and when it is reading him truly, it has been charming for him. Was going to say he doesn't see why he did it in French. Must be exquisite intellectual sport so ingenuous with the matter. No readers save for poor solitary James. Envies his equipment of knowledge and references. Wants to turn him out to fresh fields and renew his vibrations and secretions. Unfortunate that here is but one history and romantic France. What would become of his English, for which James has a sneaking fondness? His work is a gallant tribute to his French sympathies. Would he like a small volume of a couple of lectures James delivered in the United States? Wants to send something. Hasn't been published there yet. #6251-m
    - Justin, Charlotte, and Justin Huntly McCarthy to Henry James, 1905 December 18, PC (Box-folder 5:30)
      Printed Christmas greeting. #6251-an
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1905 December 28, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:31)
      Gives him an affectionate blessing. Substitute for a horrible New Year's card which he can't dishonor self or him by sending. Send a postal telling James how much he doesn't hate him. Must hold on until they meet. Miserable how months and years go by and how little they do meet. Tell him he is well, and that his strength is equal to his work, and his courage equal to his life. Hopes his work grows and lives. #6251
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Humphrey] Ward, "Tuesday night" [1905?], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:32)
      The prospect of thirty six hours with her is indeed that of "the glow, the thrill of life," after many eremite months. Fears he has a great deal more to hear than to tell. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [William] Morton [Fullerton?], 1906 January 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:33)
      Intensely moved by his beautiful letter, with sympathies as rich as lover's vows. Asks himself why strange fate keeps them so hideously separate. His perceptions and vibrations represent all the response the genius of poor James seems likely to be permitted to have become sensible of, more grateful than he can say. He is safe with him, and whole to him. Wishes some turn of the screw that will throw him with a full weight on his always Henry James. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1906 January 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:34)
      Will she come to Sesame February 12th? Will be thankful for her support. Comes to town for 3 months, and this will give him facilitation for making up arrears. He has been buried there, busy and inhuman, purely by book-making and universally dumb. Give him an early chance at her new Adelphia Terrace repoure. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1906 January 28, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:35)
      He doesn't go out to dinner: it's a proceeding he has forsworn and abhors. He would go to the stake on it; he was entrapped last summer in the hideous "midnight sun" of the Carlton. No more. Encloses ticket [not present] for her to get into the Sesame. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1906 January 31, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:36)
      Autograph note by Henry James on verso of envelope. Thanks for note and photographs of group. Speaks of this, his fine contributions to this interminable series. Criticizes "hands" and "backs" and how to improve them. Wishes he could stand in Anderson's crowed workshop and discuss these things. Patience, that will happen. Says no word of his head or his health. Only hopes he is exempt from physical woe. #6251
    - Henry James to [Angelina] Milman, 1906 February 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:37)
      Will come to tea March 1 at 5. It will be delightful to find himself again in her haunted parlor. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1906 February 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:38)
      Hoping for her sign. On the 27th, quite alone. He will be at 10 Adelphia Terrace, but make it 5 sharp. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], [1906 February 28], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. with envelope; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:39)
      Friday is impossible; now must grovel in reparations. It's death to him to meet new women and make no acquaintances. Notes, dinners, etc. are soon. Forgive this savagery. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], [1906] March 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:40)
      Can't do either; admirable and endless are her gracious bounties. Would she come to tea with him at Princess Restaurant? He has no club now where he can entertain females. Will explain his harsh unpredictability. #6251-o
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1906 March 22, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 5:41)
      Her note has a ring of sadness and sympathy. When they meet he shall urge her to meet in a more enterprising and adventurous way. Perhaps they can do something before tea. He will give her 2-3 ideas, and he shall appear in a hansom at four if she makes no contrary sign. #6251-o
    - Henry James to [Alvin Langdon] Coburn, [1906 March 23], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:42)
      His proposal about 10 Court very kind. Saw Hypolitus last night, and was so struck with it. He will return with a friend so can't avail himself of Friday, but he shall be ready for him at 105 Pall Mall at 2:30 sharp. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Violet [Hunt], 1906 May 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcript by Violet Hunt. (Box-folder 5:43)
      He has been for sometime restored to comparative calm, though the annual American flood is setting in and he is divorced from intimacy with improper person of Babylon. Forgive his atrocious manners. Will make her a sign as soon as he can steal back a little, and he has more questions about her than he can utter. #6251-o
    - Henry James to [Hendrik Christian Anderson], 1906 May 31, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:44)
      Talks of Anderson's letters and why James delays answering them. Says recent letter with Kodak views of self and family cheered him because they tell of Anderson's health, energy and might, so that James wonders at Anderson and is proud of him. His production is prodigious and heroic, very beautiful and interesting. Talks of men and ladies flaunting their bellies and bottoms and other private affairs in the face of the day. Is there any American possibility to laud them? Knows how it distresses him, but pays tribute to his noble imagination, his wealth of composition, combination, creation, and splendid sense of the body and the members. Detailed criticism follows of faces, hair, legs, etc. of the figures. Prefers to dwell on things of great beauty that Anderson constantly does. Any chance of crossing the Alps to visit him? No place so peaceful as Rye. He does well to carry a gun. #6251
    - Henry James to [Alvin] Langdon Coburn, 1906 June 8, D, 1 item. (Box-folder 5:45)
      Telegram asking if he come down Monday or Tuesday from Charing Cross, spending the night. #6251-g
    - Henry James to William James, Jr., 1906 June 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:46)
      Responding to two of his letters. Returned just yesterday having been drawn into complications of travel and time-expenditure than he at all desired, though they were enjoyable enough. The Hereford marriage was one, and was tempted to visit the wonderful Welles, where there was an exquisite cathedral where he dined with the bishop in his marbled palace. As for his lucid and excellent long letter, he sent it to his father. Doesn't see why he should be shut up at Giverny with him: of all the artists in the world! Nothing could be more satisfactory and interesting than the account you made of your actual conditions and feelings, fidelity apart. James concerned about him joining four compatriots. Make sure that he does so only if he is strongly moved to join them. Holding back on letters of introduction because he doesn't want to disturb him. #6251-av
    - Henry James to [Alvin Langdon] Coburn, [1906 June 9], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:47)
      Shall expect him Monday to stay overnight, as no good train returning to London. #6251-g
    - "Uncle" [Henry James] to Bill [William James, Jr.], 1906 June 18, TLS, 3 pp. on 2 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 5:48)